<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>learning on This is not a Monad Tutorial</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/tags/learning/</link><description>Recent content in learning on This is not a Monad Tutorial</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/tags/learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How to earn your Macroeconomics and Finance white belt (as a software developer)</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/how-to-earn-your-macroeconomics-and-finance-white-belt-as-a-software-developer/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/how-to-earn-your-macroeconomics-and-finance-white-belt-as-a-software-developer/</guid><description>I was always interested in economics. However until a few years ago I never really studied finance. Since I decided to change that, I have learnt finance from reading good and bad books, online courses, newspapers, blog posts and online forums and by executing trades. This post sums up and prioritizes the roadmap I recommend taking to learn about finance. Having a deep understanding of macroeconomics is not necessary to learn about finance, even less if you are only looking to manage your own money.</description></item><item><title>Become an Erlang Cowboy and tame the Wild Wild Web — Part I</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/become-an-erlang-cowboy-and-tame-the-wild-wild-web-part-i/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/become-an-erlang-cowboy-and-tame-the-wild-wild-web-part-i/</guid><description>Erlang: From zero to coding a commenting system Objective In the following series of posts we will be creating a commenting system like http://disqus.com/. The system will have normal HTTP/REST handlers but also some SSE and websockets handlers, and background jobs for uploading images to Amazon S3 and sending push notifications to iOS and Android clients via Amazon SNS. At the end of the series, we will connect Erlang and the system with other programming languages for those tasks that can be more difficult to do with Erlang.</description></item></channel></rss>