<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>This is not a Monad Tutorial</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/</link><description>Recent content on This is not a Monad Tutorial</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How to earn your Macroeconomics and Finance white belt (as a software developer)</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/how-to-earn-your-macroeconomics-and-finance-white-belt-as-a-software-developer/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/how-to-earn-your-macroeconomics-and-finance-white-belt-as-a-software-developer/</guid><description>I was always interested in economics. However until a few years ago I never really studied finance. Since I decided to change that, I have learnt finance from reading good and bad books, online courses, newspapers, blog posts and online forums and by executing trades. This post sums up and prioritizes the roadmap I recommend taking to learn about finance. Having a deep understanding of macroeconomics is not necessary to learn about finance, even less if you are only looking to manage your own money.</description></item><item><title>Interview with Osvaldo Martin about Bayesian Analysis with Python</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/interview_with_osvaldo_martin/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/interview_with_osvaldo_martin/</guid><description>Like our previous interviewee Osvaldo Martin is one of the developers of PyMC3 and ArviZ. He is a researcher specialized in Bayesian statistics and data science. He will be speaking at our BuzzConf this year. I hope you like this interview as much as we did!
I ‘ve created a Not a Monad Tutorial newsletter so that you receive an email whenever we publish a new story. Sign up!
Reach me via twitter at @unbalancedparen if you have any comments or interview request for This is not a Monad tutorial.</description></item><item><title>Interview with Thomas Wiecki about PyMC and probabilistic programming</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/interview-with-thomas-wiecki-about-pymc-and-probabilistic-programming/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/interview-with-thomas-wiecki-about-pymc-and-probabilistic-programming/</guid><description>A colleague of von Neumann and Ulam, Nicholas Metropolis, suggested using the name Monte Carlo, which refers to the Monte Carlo Casino in Monaco where Ulam’s uncle would borrow money from relatives to gamble”
After studying and working with distributed systems my interests drifted into data science, artificial intelligence, machine learning and now statistics. After a while I found I really liked applying what I have learnt into finance. That is how I learnt about probabilistic programming and PyMC while reading Thomas Wiecki posts at Quantopian blog.</description></item><item><title>There&#39;s more to life than HTTP, VerneMQ a high-performance and distributed MQTT broker</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/theres-more-to-life-than-htt/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/theres-more-to-life-than-htt/</guid><description>At LambdaClass and our blog This is not a Monad tutorial we are a big fans of exploring new topics, different operating systems, platforms, languages and libraries/frameworks. We have been talking in our company about exploring new subjects like protocols.
There is a whole generation of developers that has only worked with HTTP, ReST and JSON. While a partial improvement over previous technologies, it has created a protocol monoculture. There are situations where other protocols are better suited but many of the young bloods don’t even know they exist.</description></item><item><title>How to pretend you have social skills</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/how-to-pretend/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/how-to-pretend/</guid><description>A software company from another dimension
This time I decided to do something uncommon. I have asked Martina Cantaro, a psychologist that works for our company Lambdaclass, to write about the work she is doing training young developers. I hope you find it useful.
Also remember that we’ve created a Not a Monad Tutorial newsletter so that you receive an email whenever we publish a new story. Sign up!</description></item><item><title>Interview with Brad Chamberlain about a productive parallel programming language called Chapel</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/interview-with-brad-chamberlain-/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/interview-with-brad-chamberlain-/</guid><description>As you might know, I am a big fan of concurrency, parallelism and distribution but I know almost nothing about high performance computing (HPC) so I decided to get out from my comfort area. This time I’ve interviewed Brad Chamberlain about Chapel, a productive parallel programming language.
I &amp;rsquo;ve created a Not a Monad Tutorial newsletter so that you receive an email whenever we publish a new story. Sign up!</description></item><item><title>Holiday Ping, how we implemented our first open source app with Erlang and Clojurescript</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/holiday-ping-how-we-implemented-our-first-open-source-app-with-erlang-and-clojurescript/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/holiday-ping-how-we-implemented-our-first-open-source-app-with-erlang-and-clojurescript/</guid><description>After almost ten years of working as a developer for different companies, two years ago I started my own company LambdaClass. I did so because I wanted to have more freedom in choosing the type of projects and team I work with.
That is why today it is a very special day for me. We take a break from regular interviews and celebrate the release of our first open source application: Holiday Ping.</description></item><item><title>Lasp, a little further down the Erlang rabbithole</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/lasp-a-little-further-down-the-erlang-rabbithole/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/lasp-a-little-further-down-the-erlang-rabbithole/</guid><description>A few years ago I found Lasp: “a suite of libraries aimed at providing a comprehensive programming system for planetary scale Elixir and Erlang applications”. At this point it should come as no surprise for you to learn that here at Not a Monad Tutorial we are are interested in distributed systems and Erlang. After playing a little bit with Lasp I watched a few talks by its creator: Christopher Meiklejohn.</description></item><item><title>The big old reliable elephant, talking about Postgres with Craig Kerstiens</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/the-big-old-reliable-elephant-talking-about-postgres-with-craig-kerstiens/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/the-big-old-reliable-elephant-talking-about-postgres-with-craig-kerstiens/</guid><description>In this opportunity I interviewed Craig Kerstiens. Craig works for citusdata, a company that helps customers scale databases beyond a single node. Over the last few years, after building systems that used Redis, Cassandra, Riak, Elasticsearch and even Mongo, I rediscovered my love for PostgreSQL. The documentation is excellent, its development pace is astonishing and it is a good old reliable beast. However its feature set can be quite overwhelming. To mention just a few of its special features: you got a big option of index types (B-tree, Hash, GiST, SP-GiST, GIN and BRIN), many data types, extensions, window functions, common table expressions, foreign data wrappers.</description></item><item><title>Gaming with Elixir, discoverting new lands in the BEAM realm</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/gaming-with-elixir-discovering-new-lands-in-the-beam-realm/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/gaming-with-elixir-discovering-new-lands-in-the-beam-realm/</guid><description>In this opportunity I interviewed somebody I don’t normally interview: a client, Chris Jimison, CTO of Merigo. One of my clients. After working for almost a year with Merigo, I appreciate and understand the differences between using a BEAM language to develop a typical REST JSON system and using it to develop a videogame backend. I am not aware of many companies using Elixir to develop backends. I have only watch a talk by Jamie Winsor called “Building And Releasing A Massively Multiplayer Online Game”.</description></item><item><title>A Pythonist finds a new home at Clojure land</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/a-pythonist-finds-a-new-home-at-clojure-land/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/a-pythonist-finds-a-new-home-at-clojure-land/</guid><description>Welcome back to another interview of Not a Monad Tutorial. In this opportunity I decided to interview Facundo Olano, a friend, a teammate, and a developer with a diverse experience. We talked about Python, Node.js, Clojure, Common Lisp and software development in general. Something worth mentioning is that this is not the first time Python and Clojure get mentioned together at Not a Monad Tutorial. Timothy Baldridge implemented Pixie, a Lisp language inspired by Clojure, in Python.</description></item><item><title>Interview with Robert Virding, creator of Lisp Flavored Erlang, and alien technology masterpiece</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/interview-with-robert-virding-creator-of-lisp-flavored-erlang-an-alien-technology-masterpiece/</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/interview-with-robert-virding-creator-of-lisp-flavored-erlang-an-alien-technology-masterpiece/</guid><description>As you might know zombies, skeletons and momies are good friends of aliens
This time I interviewed Robert Virding, co-creator of Erlang and creator of Lisp Flavored Erlang (LFE). I am an Erlang developer and Lisp fan — if you are learning Clojure check out my post How to earn your Clojure white belt — so logically I am very excited about LFE.
Reach me via twitter at @unbalancedparen if you have any comments or interview request for This is not a Monad tutorial.</description></item><item><title>Interview with Jesper Louis Andersen about Erlang, Haskell, OCaml, Go, Idris, the JVM software and protocol design - PART II</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/interview-with-jesper-louis-andersen-about-erlang-haskell-ocaml-go-idris-the-jvm-software-and-protocol-design-part-ii/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/interview-with-jesper-louis-andersen-about-erlang-haskell-ocaml-go-idris-the-jvm-software-and-protocol-design-part-ii/</guid><description>This is part II of the interview with Jesper Louis Andersen. You can read part I here. This part of the interview is mostly about Erlang, one of my favorite languages. If you want to learn Erlang, take a look at Spawned Shelter, a website I made for Erlang newcomers.
Reach me via twitter at @unbalancedparen if you have any comments or interview request for This is not a Monad tutorial.</description></item><item><title>Interview with Jesper Louis Andersen about Erlang, Haskell, OCaml, Go, Idris, the JVM, software and protocol design - PART I</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/interview-with-jesper-louis-andersen-about-erlang-haskell-ocaml-go-idris-the-jvm-software-and-protocol-design-part-i/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/interview-with-jesper-louis-andersen-about-erlang-haskell-ocaml-go-idris-the-jvm-software-and-protocol-design-part-i/</guid><description>In this occasion we interviewed Jesper Louis Andersen, a type theorist with lot of practical knowledge and experience. His blog (you should also check his old blog, you will find a lot of good things over there) and code (specially things like safetyvalve and fuse) have been a big inspiration to me. That is why I published the interview in two parts: I had too many questions for him. I hope you enjoy reading his answers as much as I did.</description></item><item><title>Efene, an Erlang VM language that embraces the Zen of Python</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/efene-an-erlang-vm-language-that-embraces-the-zen-of-python/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/efene-an-erlang-vm-language-that-embraces-the-zen-of-python/</guid><description>In this ocasion we interviewed Mariano Guerra, creator of Efene. Efene is “an alternative syntax for the Erlang Programming Language focusing on simplicity, consistency, ease of use and programmer UX”. After reading the interview with Mariano Guerra, check Efene Quick Introduction for the Busy/Lazy Programmer for learning more about Efene.
Reach me via twitter at @unbalancedparen if you have any comments or interview request for This is not a Monad tutorial.</description></item><item><title>MLFE, ML landing in the Erlang world</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/mlfe-ml-landing-in-the-erlang-world/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/mlfe-ml-landing-in-the-erlang-world/</guid><description>Time has passed since our last interview for This is not a Monad Tutorial. OpenBSD released its 6.0 version after 20 years of continues releases without agile, OpenSSL vulnerabilities keep on breeding, Pornhub war against ad blockers continued, the Macbook Pro is not that Pro anymore, a new javascript package manager was released by Facebook and last but not least Brexit and Trump are a reality that will shape the new world order.</description></item><item><title>How to earn your Clojure white belt</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/how-to-earn-your-clojure-white-belt/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/how-to-earn-your-clojure-white-belt/</guid><description>I tend to think that if I do not know how to implement something then I do not undestand completely how it works. That is why I want to learn so many things: new frameworks, programming languages, garbage collectors, type systems, compilers, editors, operating systems, protocols, kernel development. The road to enlightenment is long and difficult. To make things worse, you need to invest time on keeping up to date with technologies you thought you already knew.</description></item><item><title>Interview with Nenad Rakocevic about Red, a Rebol inspired programming language</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/interview-with-nenad-rakocevic-about-red-a-rebol-inspired-programming-language/</link><pubDate>Fri, 28 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/interview-with-nenad-rakocevic-about-red-a-rebol-inspired-programming-language/</guid><description>After our last interview with Brian McKenna for This is not a Monad tutorial we interviewed Nenad Rakocevic, creator of the Red programming language.
From my completely subjective point of view Red and Rebol are quite strange creatures! But don’t get me wrong, that doesn’t mean something bad. For example, I am not aware of many high-level languages which features an embedded DSL for general-purpose low-level programming or that have 50 native types.</description></item><item><title>Interview with Brian McKenna about Roy, Purescript, Haskell, Idris and dependent types</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/interview-with-brian-mckenna-about-roy-purescript-haskell-idris-and-dependent-types/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/interview-with-brian-mckenna-about-roy-purescript-haskell-idris-and-dependent-types/</guid><description>As promised in our last interview for This is not a Monad tutorial we interviewed Brian McKenna, creator of the Roy programming language. In this interview Brian talks about Roy, its implementation, how it compares with Purescript, and also about dependent types and other interesting technologies like Morte and Unison. I highly recommend that you check Brian’s blog after you finish reading this interview.
In the following weeks we will be talking with the creators of Red programming language, Robert Virding — Erlang co-inventor and Lisp Flavored Erlang creator — and with MirageOS unikernel dev team.</description></item><item><title>Eric Merritt, Erlang and distributed systems expert, gives his views on BEAM languages, Hindley-Milner type sustems and new technologies</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/eric-merritt-erlang-and-distributed-systems-expert-gives-his-views-on-beam-languages-hindleymilner-type-systems-and-new-technologies/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/eric-merritt-erlang-and-distributed-systems-expert-gives-his-views-on-beam-languages-hindleymilner-type-systems-and-new-technologies/</guid><description>In this case, This is not a Monad tutorial interviewed Eric Merritt, author of Erlang and OTP in Action, Joxa (a small semantically clean, functional lisp running on the Erlang VM), relx (best release creation tool in Erlang).
In the following weeks we will be talking with Robert Virding — Erlang co-inventor and Lisp Flavored Erlang creator — , Brian McKenna —Roy language creator— and with MirageOS unikernel dev team. Stay tuned!</description></item><item><title>Harvey, an operating system with Plan 9&#39;s shadow</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/harvey-an-operating-system-with-plan-9s-shadow/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/harvey-an-operating-system-with-plan-9s-shadow/</guid><description>This is not a Monad tutorial interviewed Álvaro Jurado about the development of Harvey OS (code in github). If you haven’t yet played around with Plan 9, this will make you want to do so. Be sure to check future posts because we will be keeping an eye on the development of Harvey OS, Plan 9 derivates and Plan 9 userland tools on other operating systems.
What is Harvey OS?</description></item><item><title>Interview with Jay Kreps about Apache Kafka</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/interview-with-jay-kreps-about-apache-kafka/</link><pubDate>Sun, 22 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/interview-with-jay-kreps-about-apache-kafka/</guid><description>This time we interviewed Jay Kreps, one of the creators of Apache Kafka. Kafka is an open source messaging system with a few design choices that make it particulary useful for high throughput and low latency scenarios.
_“This experience lead me to focus on building Kafka to combine what we had seen in messaging systems with the log concept popular in databases and distributed system internals. We wanted something to act as a central pipeline first for all activity data, and eventually for many other uses, including data deployment out of Hadoop, monitoring data, etc.</description></item><item><title>Interview with Timothy Baldridge, Pixie&#39;s language creator</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/interview-with-timothy-baldridge-pixie-s-language-creator/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/interview-with-timothy-baldridge-pixie-s-language-creator/</guid><description>We interviewed Timothy Baldridge, creator of Pixie, a small fast, native lisp with magical powers. We hope you try it out!
“In modern use, Pixie can be synonymous with fairies or sprites”
Please tell us a little bit about Pixie’s inception and the road to the current status.
Timothy Baldridge
I&amp;rsquo;ve been a language hacker for years, and have played around with RPython (PyPy’s tool-chain) for some time. I&amp;rsquo;ve always had it in the back of my head that a lisp on RPython would be a good project.</description></item><item><title>One does not simply build a user interface, our ClojureScript/re-frame app</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/one-does-not-simply-build-a-user-interface/</link><pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/one-does-not-simply-build-a-user-interface/</guid><description>Part I of this article discussed the motivation to build HolidayPing and the design and development process of the back end Erlang application. In this follow-up Facundo (the main dev) focuses on the user interface and what we learnt building it.
Reach me via twitter at @unbalancedparen if you have any comments or interview request for This is not a Monad tutorial. Stay tuned!
_Discuss and vote at lobsters, reddit and hn.</description></item><item><title>Become an Erlang Cowboy and tame the Wild Wild Web — Part I</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/become-an-erlang-cowboy-and-tame-the-wild-wild-web-part-i/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/become-an-erlang-cowboy-and-tame-the-wild-wild-web-part-i/</guid><description>Erlang: From zero to coding a commenting system Objective In the following series of posts we will be creating a commenting system like http://disqus.com/. The system will have normal HTTP/REST handlers but also some SSE and websockets handlers, and background jobs for uploading images to Amazon S3 and sending push notifications to iOS and Android clients via Amazon SNS. At the end of the series, we will connect Erlang and the system with other programming languages for those tasks that can be more difficult to do with Erlang.</description></item><item><title>Is Ruby.nil? or Ruby.hype.dead? A current overview of Ruby</title><link>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/is-ruby-nil/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://catalinasy.github.io/not_a_monad_tutorial/posts/is-ruby-nil/</guid><description>The main languages I’ve used this year My last post was a really short mention of the resources I have used to learn and develop my skills in JavaScript and Erlang. On this post I’m going to share with you some thoughts I have regarding Ruby’s present.
Ruby Oh my dear Ruby, son of Lisp, Perl, Eiffel and Smalltalk, time has passed but I think you still are such an amazing creature.</description></item></channel></rss>